Science Fiction Fanzines and Ephemera Collection
Science Fiction Fanzines and Ephemera Collection
1949-1983
1.0 linear ft.
Collection of science fiction fan-generated publications (zines), science fiction convention material, clippings, photographs, and assorted other ephemera. Originally 12 linear feet, all of the zines have now been cataloged and only a few items remain in the manuscript collection.
2581782
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Science Fiction Fanzines and Ephemera Collection spans more than thirty years and contains an assortment of miscellaneous ephemera -- artwork, photographs, clippings, publicity, etc. -- relating to science fiction authors, conventions, publishers, and so on.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged alphabetically by type or title.
Related Material
has the papers of a number of science fiction authors and organizations, including the Science Fiction Writers of America; please refer to for a complete listing.
The library also holds a considerable number of science fiction books; please refer to to locate these items.
Separated Material
A list of material originally present in the collection appears in Box 1, but all of the fanzines themselves have been removed and cataloged. Please refer to to locate these items.
Subject and Genre Headings
Popular culture; Science fiction; Fan magazines.; Fantasy fiction -- Congresses.; Science fiction -- Congresses.; Fantasy fiction -- History and criticism.; Science fiction -- History and criticism.; Fantasy fiction -- Societies, etc.; Science fiction -- Societies, etc.; Book jackets.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Drawings (visual works); Newsletters.; Photographs.; Programs (documents); Science fiction fans.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Unknown.
Inventory
- Articles and clippings
  - Long after Ecclesiastes, Ray Bradbury, Orbit, 1983; poem (Box 1)
  - Professor Tolkien and the hobbits, Diplomat, Oct 1966; special section of magazine with several articles (Box 1)
  - Science fiction and fantasy, Saturday Review, Dec 1949 (Box 1)
  - Science fiction of the nuclear age, Johns Hopkins Magazine, Mar 1977 (Box 1)
  - The threat of creationism, Isaac Asimov, New York Times Magazine, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Through space and time with Forrest Ackerman, New West, 28 Jan 1980 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1964; 1970,; 1973,; 1980; on various science fiction-related topics (Box 1)
- Conventions
  - Con-Committee Chairman's Guide, by George Scithers (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, fliers, registration forms, posters, etc. (Box 1)
- Fanzines and newsletters
  The vast majority of these items have been cataloged. Please refer to to locate these items.
  - List of titles (original), complete list of what was originally in the collection (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Movies and films
  - Miscellaneous, movie press releases, movie and film societies, etc. (Box 1)
- People and organizations
  - Cogswell, Theodore, 1975; Christmas card (Box 1)
  - Ellison, Harlan, 1980-1981; article by Ellison for Writer's Digest, few items of correspondence (Box 1)
  - Heinlein, Robert, 1972; brochure for Forrestal Lecture Series, featuring Heinlein (Box 1)
  - International Aviation Writer's Association, 1957; text of speech on legal aspects of space travel (Box 1)
  - NASA (National Aeronatics and Space Administration), Kennedy Space Center material, teacher's guide on the planets, list of names given to surface features near the Apollo 15 landing site, etc. (Box 1)
  - Science Fiction Writers of America (SFWA), 1966-1978; correspondence, mailings, ballots, etc.; much of it pertains to the Nebula Awards; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Zelazny, Roger, few items of correspondence, publicity poster for Madwand, "Working bibliography" compiled by Phil Stephensen-Payne, photocopy of "My lady of the diodes" (Box 1)
  - Zelazny, Roger (cont.), article by Zelazny on writing for children, miscellaneous items from a Russian fan (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Photographs and artwork
  - Artwork, original, original art by unidentified artists, mostly pen and ink (Box 2)
  - Artwork, reproduction, line art illustrations for Dragons of Darkness, Pocket, possibly others (Box 2)
  - Photographs, living "pods" on alien planet, possibly a movie set? (Box 2)
- Publishers and books
  - Avon, mostly press releases about upcoming SF titles (Box 2)
  - Ballantine, publicity posters and book lists for their Del Rey line of SF (Box 2)
  - Bantam (Box 2)
  - Carcosa, press release for its first title (Box 2)
  - Pocket Books, includes numerous issues of "Timescape," their science fiction newsletter (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, includes several jacket proofs and some used book lists (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous
  - Atomic Clock, 1959; packet of material pertaining to the atomic clock and its use in testing Einstein's theory of relativity (Box 2)
  - Correspondence (Box 2)
  - Printed material, Japanese issue of Omni magazine, poster for "Science fiction at your library!", etc.; 2 folders (Box 2)